Hi everyone. This
lecture will focus on the
pharmacological management
of dyslipidemia.
So I will go through the
types of dyslipidemias
and I will briefly review
some of the pathophysiology,
the idea of aproproteins
and what they
do, and then I'll go
through the major classes.
And of course, as
of now, the gold
standard is going
to be the statins.
So with that, I will go
through each class and
I will talk about some of
the adverse effects and
the main drug interactions.
I will also go
through which class targets
which. So for example,
if we're talking about the
LDL lowering, then we talk
about statins. If it's
triglycerides, we're going to
rely on fibrates. I'll also
talk about some of the newer
monoclonals that are used to
manage hyperlipidemia that
doesn't respond to anything,
especially in those
patients that have familial
hyperlipidemia. And then I'll
go through the guidelines,
but again, I will ask you
not to memorize them. I will
ask you to know mainly the
mechanisms, the adverse
effects and drug interactions.
Back to dyslipidemia, we
have primary and secondary.
Primary really points
to that there's
a mutation in
some of the genes.
As you can see on
the right-hand side,
you're going to have
some dependence on the
LDL receptor. Something
is not functioning.
There may be an increase
in PCSK9, and that is going
to affect, again, the LDL
receptors. There's also
going to be some effects on
Apro B100 because that is
the ligand by which the LDL
binds to. So those are the
main mechanisms for familial
hypercholesterolemia.
And with these genetic
components, you're
going to see that
these patients will
have early onset
of atherosclerosis.
For secondary
hypercholesterolemia, that tends to
point through maybe
lifestyle, other medications,
and even conditions, if
we're talking about the
relationship between
hypothyroidism and even type
2 diabetes in patients
that have hyperlipidemia.
With patients that have
high triglycerides,
that's defined as when
you see in the lipid
panel that level is
above 150. And I will
say usually we don't
start treatment until
you see 500 or more. That
is considered to be severe.
And the reason why we would
start medications is that
you run the risk of the
patient having pancreatitis.
And then with the familial,
as I spoke about, we have
heterozygous. And that is
usually due to the fact
that that patient maybe had
one parent with a mutation.
And there's a problem,
again with the LDL receptor.
Homozygous, you're going
to see the patient's
LDL being sometimes
above 500. This is when
the two genes are
mutated and that's the
composite. Maybe there's
something happening with
the LDL receptor with
PCSK9 or apoproteins.
So just a little bit
about lipoproteins
And the idea here is transport.
That's what I can say
that they are involved.
So as you can see,
the chylomicrons are
considered to be the biggest.
And these are going to be
involved in transporting
fat from the intestine.
So say after a meal,
they're going to be
responsible for taking the
fat to the blood or the
muscle or the fat tissue.
As you can see, after
that, we have VLDL,
and those are very low
-density lipoproteins.
IDL are in the middle.
Low-density is LDL. And
remember, with LDL, that
is what is going to carry
cholesterol from the liver
to the circulation. And
the biggest concern is
going to be the arteries.
And then as you can see,
HDL, as you can
imagine, the diameter
is small, yet it's
called high density.
And HDL is responsible now
for carrying cholesterol
from the tissues to the
liver for breakdown.
So when we talk about
a lipid panel, we
want to see the LDL
being low as possible.
But with HDL, you're
always encouraged that
you want this level to
be higher because you
want more of them so it
can be carried from the
circulation back to the
liver for breakdown.
So the apoproteins, if I had
to say, what's their role?
They're going to act as
ligands to bind lipids.
They're going to act
as transporters. And
ApoB100 is the ligand
for the LDL receptor.
It's also involved in
secreting the LDL from
the liver. So you can
say that when it comes to
LDL receptors, what
can raise receptors is
usually going to be the
statins. There'll be
others, but that's the
key class of medication.
Apple 48 is going
to be secreting
chylomicrons from
the intestines.
And then we have Apple
A1. When I think about
that medication, I think
about HDL. And probably
with HDL, you're going to
see activation of LCAT.
And I'll talk about that
in a couple of moments.
The drug that we
have that actually
can raise HDL is
going to be niacin.
Aside from that, you
raise your HDL by
not smoking, by
exercising, by your diet.
And then you're going
to have the Apple C.
Apple C2 is going
to activate LPL.
And that is going
to be the mechanism
of what we see
with the fibrates.
And that is going to be
involved mainly with VLDL.
Apple C3 is an inhibitor
of LPL. So if anything, you
kind of want to lower your
apple C3 while increasing
apple C2, which we can say
again that maybe fibrates
have a participation in
those two apple proteins.
So what is LPL?
Well, it's going to be
present in the endothelium
because it's going to be where
it breaks down triglycerides
and the fibrates are
going to act in that area.
So they're going
to degrade LPL.
Triglycerides in the
bloodstream, and that's a good
thing, and that's why we
want an enhancement of LPL.
They're also going to shrink
the chylomicrons, and if
you're shrinking them,
you're going to decrease
triglycerides and ultimately
you'll decrease pancreatitis.
So remember, LPL is going to be
present in the
endothelial cells.
So some of what happens
with lipoprotein
metabolism. As you can
see, we will have a meal in
which the small intestines
will absorb fat.
And there is a class of
drug. Actually, it's one
drug that's called
azitimbi that can work
there. It works on the
Neiman-Pick transporter.
You see now you're going
to get formation, okay,
of chylomicrons
because as I mentioned,
they're going to
transport the fat from
the intestines into
the blood and beyond.
And once you get a
chylomicron, then you're going
to get some hydrolysis of
the chylomicron chylomicron
by LPL, lipoprotein
lipase. And you're going
to get two things, the
formation of free fatty acids,
which can go to the
adipose and muscle tissue.
And then you're
going to have some
remnants, which then
go to the liver.
And then at the liver,
you're going to get now
chylomicrons are going
to be now becoming VLDL.
LPL comes in again, you
create intermediate density,
lipoproteins. And as you
can see now, ultimately you
get more LPL and that is
going to in fact create LDL.
And you can see again,
as I mentioned in
that previous slide,
that what is going to be
associated with
chylomicrons is Apple B48.
And then with LDL, again,
it's going to be Apple B100.
So HDL is going to be involved
in reverse cholesterol
transport. Very easy because
that's going to take the
cholesterol from the
circulation back to the liver.
And as you can see, you're
going to get the participation
of apoprotein A1, and
you're going to get
participation of this LCAT.
And this is an enzyme that
is known as the lecithin
cholesterol acetyltransferase.
And what this enzyme
does, it enables HDL to
pick up cholesterol. So the
more of that LCAT that you
have, the more you're
going to allow now the
cholesterol to go back to the
liver and get broken down.
And there's actually
some patients that might
have a mutation in the
LCAT enzyme, and that can
actually decrease HDL.
Okay, so ultimately, you
want to get immature
HDL to become mature and
to allow this enzyme to
pick up more cholesterol
to take back to the
liver to be broken down.
So the LDL receptor,
as I mentioned,
you have
the participation
of apoprotein B100,
that's its ligand,
and it's made up of a
monolayer of phospholipids
and cholesterol.
Inside or the
core, you're going
to get esters and
triacylglycerols.
And then LDL is going
to bind to receptors.
That's going to be taken
into the cell, and you're
going to get receptor
-mediated endocytosis.
What's there is going to
get broken down, and then
you're going to get the
recycling back up of the LDL
receptor to do this again.
So we want to say that diet,
exercise are a component of
lowering cholesterol. But
sometimes people could be
doing the right thing and it
might be just due to the
fact that perhaps they don't
have enough LDL receptors to
clear out their cholesterol.
Okay, so a receptor
participation patient is also
involved. And many of the
drugs that we'll talk about
do have an improvement of
LDL receptors, so to speak.
So with atherosclerosis,
as you can
see, in the normal
human artery,
you see that there's a
nice balance between the
endothelium and the smooth
muscle. okay with respect to
damage or the beginning
of atherosclerosis number
one there's going to be
some damage of the artery
wall as you can see and that
is going to allow now LDL
to start becoming trapped
inside and with that the
body is going to respond
through an immune mechanism
the endothelium is going
to start recruiting
macrophages and that along
with the fact that LDL is
getting oxidated is going
to switch these macrophages
into foam cells and then
you're going to get a
formation of fatty streaks
and then you know of course
if you start getting to the
point where now platelets
start aggregating that
is going to be a thrombus
and that will result in
some type of ischemia, okay?
So, the drugs for hyperlipidemia.
I will go through to,
in essence, the sites of
action. So, in the GI tract,
you're going to have bile
acid resins working there,
okay? They're going to,
in essence, what will
happen is you lose bile
acids because you inhibit
enterohepatic circulation
of bile acids.
You lose them in your
feces, and now you're
going to need cholesterol
to replace those
bile acids. So that's
how these drugs work.
The other thing is,
as I talked about, the
ezitimbi, that's going
to act in the intestines.
It's going to affect
a transporter known as
Neiman-Pick, and that's
going to decrease
cholesterol from your
diet from being absorbed.
In the liver, there's going
to be now synthesis of
cholesterol, and that's
going to be done by statins,
even benpadoic
acid, and I'll speak
about that a little bit later.
And then the inhibition
of VLDL secretion
is going to be
achieved by niacin.
And then lastly, when
I talked about the
endothelial cells in
lipoprotein lipase,
there's going to be activation
of that enzyme by fibrates.
Okay.
So bile acid resins,
as you can see, there's
three of them. We
have cholesthyramine,
cholesterol,
and cholecevolam.
Cholecevolam is
known as Wellcol.
It's available as a tablet.
The only issue is that
it has to be given,
I believe, three
tablets twice a day.
these drugs have and the
other two are are available
as powders and that
sometimes can be annoying
because it's almost
like if you think about
metamucil you have to
put this powder in enough
fluid and drink it and
some people will find that
cumbersome but then
again the tablets may be
annoying because you got
to take a bunch of tablets
three in the morning and
three in the evening.
There is no bioavailability
with these drugs. They're
not absorbed, and that can
be a good thing in certain
populations. So you're going
to prevent the enterohepatic
recirculation of bile
acids. So by doing that,
you're going to use up the
cholesterol to replace those
bile acids. It's kind of a
very interesting mechanism.
The other thing is that
it can increase LDL
receptor formation.
And all in all, the LDL
blood levels go down by
30%. Not too bad, but
obviously not as
impressive as the statins.
Sometimes we use these drugs
in protocols. So there is
some use of them, say if
you wanted to bind like
digoxin. But remember with
digoxin, you're going to have to
be more concerned about
electrolytes, the potassium,
the magnesium.
But if it was still
in the gut, you could
use this drug or
Digibind. And that'll
come in some future
lectures in this block.
The other thing that we can
use these drugs is to stop
pruritus in patients with
cholestasis because they're
going to bind those bile
acids. And patients that
have this problem are going
to get this itch due to the
bile acids. The issue is
it's going to work in the
GI. So patients will complain
of nausea, of bloating,
of constipation, and it's
going to interfere with drug
absorption, just like I
spoke about with adoxin. So
the idea here is if you
need to take medication like
say a thiazide or levothyroxine,
you're going to need
to space it apart by several
hours. So again, if you
needed to take your Synthroid
or maybe your vitamin D,
best thing is to take
them and then maybe take
your cholestyramine
maybe two hours later.
The other thing to note is
since they're not absorbed,
they are acceptable if you
have a pregnant patient
that is needing some type of
medication for hyperlipidemia
because we know that
statins are contraindicated.
With peds, they're also
another viable alternative,
although statins are
now getting some use in
the pediatric population
in those kids that are
over 10 years old. But
again, a bile acid resin
could be an alternative
because it's not absorbed.
So as you can see in
this picture, if you are
inhibiting the entero
-hepatic circulation of
bile acids you're going
to get rid of your
bile acids and now
you're going to again use
up the cholesterol to
create more bile acids.
And one thing to note is
that there is an effect here
with 7-alpha-hydroxylase
and that is the rate
limiting step in bile
acid synthesis. So
that That, in fact, is
going to be enhanced,
and that too is going
to increase bioacids.
So nicotinic acid, or
niacin, or vitamin B3,
will inhibit lipolysis
in the adipocytes.
And the way it works, as
you can see in the picture,
it's going to stabilize or
mobilize free fatty acids.
So by doing that, as you
can see in the liver,
it's going to decrease
triglycerides, and
it's going to decrease,
obviously, VLDL secretion.
And then on this side,
as you decrease VLDL,
you're going to decrease
LDL, and that is
going to create more of
an enhancement of HDL.
okay so as you can see there
is some modest reduction
of the LDL and LDL but it
has of all the medications
the highest increase
of HDL okay and again
stabilizing free fatty acids
so when do we use this well
understand that there's a
couple of adverse effects
that might make this
annoying. Number one, you can
buy niacin over the counter,
but if you know anything
about that, it's available
as a sustained release.
Because what happens is that
patients, when they begin
the medication or there's
an increase in dose,
they're going to get a severe
intense flush and itch.
It can be prevented with
an NSAID because it's
prostaglandin mediated, but
it is somewhat annoying.
There may be some effects on
blood sugar, hyperglycemia.
It could be due to the
fact that it may affect
the secretion of insulin
from the pancreas. There may
be some increase in
gluconeogenesis from the liver.
With hyperuricemia, we
tend to think that with
these medications, there's
going to be a recovery
of uric acid from the kidney,
and that can complicate
somebody that has gout.
And then when it comes
to peptic ulcer disease,
it might be due to the
fact that it may allow
some acid release from
the parietal cells, and
that's histamine related.
The other thing is if
you were to take this
medication and you were
also using a statin,
you may put your patient at
a greater risk of myalgia.
And that's a very real
adverse effect when we combine
statins with niacin or
statins even with fibrates.
And then, again,
we don't have much
data on how it's
affecting pregnancy,
so we say not to
use it in pregnancy.
Again, the flushing is due
to the fact that you're
getting vasodilation, and
that is going to create this
intense feeling of flushiness,
because that's an increase
in blood flow, and somewhat
of a redness. So the
way you would manage it,
you could give a NSAID for a
few days or you can give a
slow-release formulation.
So HMGA-CoA
reductase inhibitors.
So as you can see here,
okay, and I'll talk about
bempadoic acid a
little bit later.
This is the rate-limiting step
of cholesterol synthesis, okay?
And statins will act as
competitive inhibitors,
okay? The other thing is
that they will increase the
number of LDL receptors.
And we have seen that with
LDL, it's 45% or maybe even
more when we're talking
about lowering LDL. So
it's extremely impressive.
And this was one of the
first studies that they
did because simvastatin
was among the first statin
that came to the market.
And what they did in
the Scandinavia, they
gave 4-4-4-4 angina heart
attack patients with a
cholesterol of 2-10 to 3-10.
They put them on simvastatin
for about five and
a half years. And what
they saw is that their
LDL went down by 35%.
deaths went down by 30%, and
cardiac deaths specifically
went down by 42%.
And these studies have
been shown over and over
to have a benefit. So
in the United States, if
you look up the top five
medications every year,
it's always in the
list is atorvastatin.
Okay, so it's
usually atorvastatin,
maybe amlodipine, lisinopril,
Synthroid. Those are
usually in the top five.
In some years, it just
is consistent that
atorvastatin is like
the number one drug.
And the reason being is
through these studies that
have shown that giving these
medications is actually
a benefit. Not only does
it, you know, prevent
atherosclerosis, it prevents
death from cardiac diseases.
So this is probably the reason
why that they're
so widely used.
So we'll go through the
adverse effects. Since
the action is happening in
the liver, we can expect
some hepatotoxicity.
okay so when you start
these medications you
should do liver function
test if the patient is a
person that uses a lot of
alcohol or they have
liver dysfunction you may
need to have a conversation
with them or if it's
really that bad you may
use another medication
myopathy can happen
and the problem
with the myopathy is if you get
breakdown of the muscle,
you may get rhabdomyolysis.
And that's where the patient
now is going to get some
issues with, number one,
their kidneys. And the other
thing is that you'll see it
in the urine. So you want to
draw a creatine kinase level.
The urine will be dark.
They say that there may be
some increase in fasting
glucose levels. Again,
that is like very rare,
okay? It may be due to
the fact that in the
liver, some patients
may get an increase in
gluconeogenesis, or it
may be due to the fact
that GLUT4, which is
responsible for taking up
sugar into the
adipose tissue and to
the liver, that might
be also affected.
But again, this is
very rare, and for the
most part, if you have
a patient that is also
diabetic, they're
probably going to be on
other medications for
the diabetes as well.
The issue becomes
when the patient is
taking an enzyme
inhibitor. So that's
going to be
cimetidine, the azoles,
grapefruit juice, and
this is where, you
know, the issue comes
because, you know, I have
had patients in
practice that, you know
they're taking statins
and then they go to the
dermatologist and they
have a nail fungus
and they get an azole
sporinox or itraconazole
prescribed and that
warning would all
always come up and i would
say to them does your
dermatologist know
you're taking a statin
and the answer is no
why would i why does my
dermatologist need to know
that i have high cholesterol.
And that's where being
very cognizant about asking
your patients what
medication they're taking is
very important. Because that
patient, even if they've
been well controlled on
their statin, they never
had any adverse effects,
their LFTs came out nice,
they may now get an increase
in now statin levels
just before taking that
medication for nail fungus.
In pregnancy, these are not
indicated. They say that
statins can have an effect
on some of the proteins that
are involved in development.
I think they're called
Hodge proteins. There's also
the idea that in order to
create membranes and hormones,
you need cholesterol.
So you need to be mindful
of the balance. In pediatric
patients, especially the
ones that have the familial
hyperlipidemia you
can't start the
medication if
they're 10 and older
it used to be that statins
had to be taken in the
evenings because cholesterol
is actually produced that
night so they would tell
us that the best time to
take a statin would be
during that period. However,
the newer drugs like
atorvastatin, rosuvastatin,
have been, they have
really improved the
pharmacokinetics that they
can take it at any time.
And then there's something
called red yeast rice.
You can look it up on
Google. It looks like red
and grainy. And this is
a supplement that is over
the counter. And the issue
is that, again, we don't
support supplements because
they're not approved.
They don't do clinical
trials. But this was
advertised as being a
medication that can, in fact,
lower cholesterol. And maybe
it's true, but the issue
became that I had one patient
who was on a statin and
was advised by his neighbor
to use this and incidentally
he started to have myalgia
and when we further
questioned him we found out
that he was taking that and
so we we sent him to the
physicians to draw out labs
he stopped the red yeast
rice and when you look up
the possible mechanism they
say it could have an effect
almost like a statin. So
again, the idea of supplements
is pretty serious because
patients always think
that they're safe and they
can bite over the counter
and their friend told them
and they did well. But again,
they need to understand
if they're taking other
medications, they really need
to get the right guidance.
Okay, so the myopathy.
So number one,
on their own, statins
really don't have an effect
on the muscle. There becomes
an issue when they're
taking medications that have
SIP inhibition or they're
taking it with fibrates
or with niacin, okay?
And that's important. And
I told you that, you know,
fibrates, you know, one
of the reasons why we wait
until it's 500 in order
to start a fibrate
to stop the pancreatitis
is that many times
the patients are already
taking the statin.
And the issue is that
there can be a decrease in
ubiquinone. And with ubiquinone,
what it is responsible for
doing is to increase
everything that's happening in
the electron transport chain.
It helps make energy. So
the proposal is that statins
perhaps block ubiquinone,
and that's why patients
start getting muscle pain and
weakness because of that
loss of energy to the muscle.
And again, coenzyme Q10,
there has been, you know,
some discussion about
that. Some doctors say it's
okay. Some doctors don't
believe in it. I will
tell you that they have
done some clinical trials
on coenzyme Q10, and they
have not really found
something that is consistent
with recommending. So
again, if it was up to
me, I probably wouldn't.
And again, most patients
that have hyperlipidemia
will have other medications
on board. And that's
something that we don't
know. Will it interfere with
your diabetes medication?
Does it affect their aspirin?
Does it affect their
hypertension medications?
So that's just something
you might see in passing.
So LFT monitoring, this has
changed in the past year.
You always want to do a
baseline, and that's important.
Whenever you start
medication, you want to do a
CMP. You want to check the
liver and the renal function.
I can't say that enough.
If you were giving them
lisinopril, I would
definitely want
to look at the
potassium levels.
And then they say about
8 to 12 weeks, you want
to call them back, you
want to check their
lipid panel, and you would
also look at their LFTs.
But once that happens,
and they don't have
any symptoms, you don't
have to do it routinely.
And that may be the case,
but you're still going
to want to check the
lipid panel. So my idea
is why not just check
everything. But again,
this is again the reason
why I would never test
this on an exam because
it's always changing.
ALT or AST, if it's
consistently greater
than three times
the upper limit
of normal, you should
stop the statin.
And then this is definitely
true. If that patient is
taking other medications
and they are using SIP
inhibitors, I would definitely
take the level of their
liver function test. Same
thing with those patients
that use a lot of alcohol,
because we know that there
is a risk of hepatotoxicity
with these medications.
okay other things to consider
is is the diet lack of
exercise smoking hypothyroidism
okay what's the deal
with that well number one
when you are low in thyroid
hormone there is some
decrease in LDL receptors.
So, hypothyroid can be
associated with hyperlipidemia.
Type 2 diabetes, again,
because you start to think
about, you know, diet and
glucose and, you know,
the relationship
between glucose and fat,
calories, and that's true
of alcohol intake as well.
And then, again, with respect
to the high homocysteine.
High homocysteine is
associated with an increase
in reactive oxidative
species. That can affect
the wrestles. It can
increase clot formation.
And then you have drugs
which increase lipid
levels. And this is
important. Any of the hormone,
especially the oral
contraceptives whether
it be progesterone
only or estrogen and
progesterone that can
increase lipid levels.
Anabolic steroids,
protease inhibitors, so
remember those are drugs
that affect the maturation
of the virus that
can create an increase
in triglycerides and LDL.
Glucocorticoids can do this,
atypical antipsychotic.
So remember, from last
year, we went through
the fact that the D2
receptor blockers, we were
not happy with them because
they cause neurological.
They cause EPS,
Parkinsonism, increase in
prolactin. So many people
are taking Risperdone.
They're taking Olanzapine.
And what happens with
those medications? They're
all patients will eat more.
And we start to see now
with those medications,
patients will have an elevated
A1C and even a lipid panel
and even the retinoids.
So it's important, again,
when you screen the patient
for hyperlipidemia, you
also look at what other
things they may be taking.
I'm not going to test
you on the AHA, ACC
guidelines, but just
understand that if the patient
has an LDL cholesterol
of greater than 190,
you want to give them a
high intensity statin,
okay? Other than that, it
depends. You have to do
the score, okay? So for
example, if you have somebody
between 40 and 75 and they
have diabetes and they
have a high risk of getting
a MI in 10 years, then
you would do a moderate
or high intensity statin.
I will say that
with this, they're
even making it even younger.
I did see something
not too long ago
that they're saying,
you know, even
at 30, you should
start medication.
Some will start the
medication even younger than
that. So again, it's important
to know the guidelines,
but you really have to
know the patient you really
have to see what their
overall score is okay if they
are a patient that you know
has everything on board
they're they're smokers
they they have you know
high a1c they have hypertension
then yes you probably
would need to start them
on statin therapy okay
and i will say that with
respect to statins, you know,
another thing that's come
up in, I would say, in
the influencer community
is this idea that statins
can cause dementia. And,
you know, here's the thing.
In reality, statins can
actually be beneficial
for certain dementias.
They actually can
prevent vascular dementia,
because if you think
about it, when we're
talking about people that
get vascular dementia,
most of them have
something on board, like
hypertension, they have
hyperlipidemia, they
have high glucose
levels, so they're
actually protective.
The other thing is that
statins may decrease
inflammation, and that's
always a good thing.
um and the other thing about
dementia is that the fact
that you know older people
are more prone to dementia
and it seems like older
people are also taking statin
medications so it may not
be a medication problem it
may be just the population
that's aging is on more
medications and they start
seeing other things happening,
okay? But, you know,
that's another, you know,
concept where, you know,
people have asked me, well,
I saw on, you know,
Instagram that somebody's
saying that they're
causing, you know, dementia.
And the answer is right
now, no. They're actually
preventive against
especially vascular dementia.
The dosing of statins,
the high intensity are
going to be atorvastatin and
vesuvastatin, and the
moderate intensity are going
to be the same, but at
lower dosages. And as
mentioned, the reason why
atorvastatin and vesuvastatin
are preferred is because
they can be taken at
any time of day. If I
was giving somebody, say,
simvastatin, which is Zocor,
I might tell them, you
know, take it at night.
But the two most popular
ones, there's really no
regard to when they take it.
So now we have fibrates.
And we have genfibrizil
and phenylfibrate.
As you can see, there's
FIB in the middle.
And that should
give you a clue that
anything with fib in
the middle is a fibrate.
So what is happening here?
Well, there is a nuclear
transcription that's
happening. And it has to do
with a ligand called, a
receptor called PPAR-alpha.
And the drug will
bind, acting as a
ligand, and activate
this receptor. And once
it does, it's going
to increase LPL.
And remember, with LPL,
that's going to lead to fatty
acid oxidation, and it's
going to break down VLDL.
And as you can see, fibrates
are going to enhance.
Going back to the original,
what I was talking about,
it's going to increase
apoprotein C2.
It's going to decrease
apoprotein C3 because
those are inverses when
it comes to LPL action.
So ultimately, you may
get some increase in
HDL and you're going
to increase your VLDL.
And you see that with
lowering triglycerides,
you're going to get an
almost 35% reduction.
Some of the adverse effects
is that this medication
may decrease 7-alpha
-hydroxylase. So it's
the opposite of what we
saw with the bile acid
resins. And because
you're reducing 7-alpha
-hydroxylase, you're going
to decrease bile acids.
And that means you're going
to have more cholesterol
in the bile than bile acids
because you've reduced
bile acids. And if there's
more cholesterol in
that area, you're going to
increase stones. So that
is where the risk of
gallstones comes from, the
fact that vibrates can
decrease 7-alpha-hydroxylase.
And then with respect
to the statins,
if you put a statin
with a fibrate,
you may get an increase in
myalgia and rhabdomyolysis,
and that can lead
ultimately to renal injury.
So, EZ-TIMBY is going to
work in the small intestines.
It's going to bind to
the Neiman-Pick C1-like-1
transporter. And because of
that, you're not going to get
now fat coming into to the
small intestine. So it's
going to affect, you know,
at first the chylomicrons.
Putting it together with
the statin is going to
cause further reduction
of LDL, which is a good
thing. But you also
need to watch the liver
function because you
may have the two of them
together may have an effect
on the liver enzymes.
Other than that,
azitimbis, since
it's working in the
intestines, may
cause some GI upset.
So now we have the PCSK9
inhibitors. These are considered
to be medications that
are monoclonal antibodies,
okay? They are
given subcutaneously
either every two
weeks or once a month.
And what's happening with
this group is that by
inhibiting this protein,
you're going to decrease LDL
receptor degradation. And
that goes back to what
I said before. it's not just
about diet and exercise,
it's about the availability
of LDL receptors.
So these are not going
to be first line anytime
soon because they are
considered to be somewhat
expensive, but these are
going to be reserved for those
patients that have familial
hypercholesterolemia
or they have evidence of
early atherosclerosis,
okay, and maybe the statin
alone is not working well.
So they would give this
medication with an appropriate
diet and also maximum
tolerated statin. And you
see that the LDL in APO 100
reduction is significant.
What will happen
with these two,
you can get some
hypersensitivity.
You can get some
injection site reactions.
So you can manage
that with maybe a cold
compress, maybe some
topical hydrocortisone.
Myalgia can definitely
happen if this
is given in fact
with the statin.
And then again, this
issue of neurocognitive
effects has come up and
the increase in dementia.
Again, with these medications,
they don't cross the
blood-brain barrier. So that
is one thing that supports
the use of these medications
and negates this theory.
But again, you may see this
in passing, on websites,
but just understand that
reducing cholesterol
reduces atherosclerosis.
It does reduce some
of the inflammation
that's even happening in
the brain. So, most of
the evidence is supporting
the use of these
medications in patients.
The next medication is going
to be, you know, incasarin.
This is a very
interesting drug because
it kind of goes
one step further.
it's going to decrease
messenger RNA that makes
PCSK9 so if you're stopping
PCSK9 from being made
you're going to preserve
your LDL because there's no
protein to degrade it so
that is going to result
again an increase in receptors
the other good thing is
you know again and it's
going to be pricey, it's
given subcutaneously twice
a year, okay? And that's
also a good thing when we
talk about convenience.
Lomitapide is a very
rarely used medication.
And the only reason
why I'm mentioning
it is if patients
that are homozygous
and they have the
familial hyperlipidemia.
And remember, those
are the ones that had
the two copies where
their LDL was over 500.
They're at great
risk of getting early
atherosclerosis and
cardiovascular disease.
This one is going to
inhibit this protein, okay?
And it's going to do it
in the intestines. and as
you can see APOB48 which
is responsible for making
chylomicrons and then
it's going to block again
MTP in the liver and that
is responsible for creating
ultimately VLDL and it's
the ligand for LDL and
this is known as microsomal
triglyceride transfer
protein And basically what
it's doing by blocking
here, it's going to stop
APOB48 in the intestines
from assembling triglycerides.
And in the liver,
it's going to stop APOB100
from assembling VLDL.
Okay, so what's wrong
with this medication?
Well, it's reserved for
these patients because
it has a severe risk
of hepatotoxicity.
If VLDL cannot be
assembled, okay, and you
can see it here on
the right-hand side,
what is going to happen
is that VLDL is going
to accumulate in the
liver and that's going
to increase the risk
of fatty liver. It's
going to increase your
liver function test.
not to be given pregnancy
if you have anything on
board that is a SIP inhibitor
you're going to raise
the levels of this and that
will increase your risk
of liver injury okay if it's
given with statins again
back to the liver you're
going to raise toxicity so
in order for this to be
given it's not going to be
prescribed in the pharmacy
but it's going to be
through a program it's called
REMS, and I think we saw
it last year when we talked
about one of the drugs
we use for postpartum, and
I think one of the drugs
that we use for cataplexy,
and I think it was sodium
oxyburate that we used for
those patients that had
cataplexy with narcolepsy.
It's not something that's easy,
that needs to be paperwork
filed, and the patient
and the physician have to go
through rigorous criteria.
But again, this would be an
option for those patients
that have homozygous from
myelohypolipidemia. And
as I mentioned, it's very
rare, but it is severe.
The next one is the omega
-3 fatty acids. And if
I had to say, you know,
how do these drugs work?
They're going to act
somewhat like a fibrate.
They're going to agonize
the PPAR-alpha, and
they're going to stimulate
lipoprotein lipase.
A couple of other
things that they can do
besides reduce
hypertriglyceridemia is that
they do have an anti
-inflammatory mechanism.
The other thing is that
they decrease thromboxane
and they increase
prostacycline and that can be
an anti-thrombotic effect,
which may be a good
thing. But in some patients
that can lead to bleeding
and this becomes a concern
when a patient, say,
is taking aspirin or
clopidogrel or an anticoagulant.
They may have an increased
risk of bleeding.
The EPA DHA is sold over the
counter and as a prescription,
and that, I believe,
is known as Lovasa.
And then you have EPA only.
And EPA only, again, goes
back to the fact that it
reduces ApoC3. And remember,
that's the one that
actually had a negative
effect on LPL. It actually
lowered LPL. So if you're
reducing that, then you
increase LPL, and that is the
reason why it's a good option
for high triglycerides.
And that medication is
known as icosapent ethyl.
So, bimpedalic acid, very
interesting medication.
This is an oral form,
okay? But here's the thing.
It's not really, it's not
going to affect ubiquinone.
So, it's got a good profile,
okay? at reducing LDL,
but it's not going to cause
the myalgia of statins,
so you see less myopathy
with benpedolic acid.
It also increases
LDL receptors.
So how does it
work? So as you can
see, this is where
the statins work.
These are working
almost, you know,
backwards. They're
going to affect an
enzyme known as
ATP citrate Lysed,
okay? So, it's going to
stop the conversion of
citrate to acetyl-CoA
because from acetyl-CoA,
then you get an HMG-CoA
and then you have the
enzyme that ultimately
creates cholesterol. So,
it's coming from like
backwards, so to speak,
the enzyme is being blocked
here from the TCA cycle
so as I said it's another
option for patients that
have myopathy
associated with statin
therapy so again, are
they first line? no,
it's an option
for those patients
that can't tolerate statins
some of the adverse effects
Number one, hyperuricemia,
that might be due to the
fact that the drug can
inhibit the organic acid
transporters, and that can
lead now to more recovery
of uric acid in the kidney.
There also may be an
increased risk of tendon
rupture that we see sometimes
with fluoroquinolones.
That tends to happen in
older adults and maybe
patients that are taking
glucocorticoids. So again, if
the patient gets severe
pain in, say, their ankles,
they should let their
physician know as soon
as possible. Okay, so
this is bimpedalic acid.
And then we have a newer one
that is a monthly infusion.
And this one is evinocumab.
And the indication
is, again, for homozygous
familial hyperlipidemia.
This is going to block
a specific peptide,
and it's known as
angiopoedin-like 3.
So when you block this
peptide here with this
monoclonal, what you're going
to do is going to increase
two enzymes. Number
one, lipoprotein lipase.
Okay.
And that again is going
to take care of your
triglycerides and VLDL. And
you're also going to affect
endothelial lipase. So
together you have this double
action and that is going
to break down all of them.
Okay. Some of the adverse
effects, there can be
injection site reactions,
which you can pre-treat.
And there might be some
anaphylaxis. But again, this
is not going to be given
on an outpatient. They will
probably, you know, be in
a facility. So there'll be
people on board to monitor
if they get any anaphylaxis.
So in summary, when
we're thinking about
LDL reduction and
increasing receptors.
Bile acid resins will
lose cholesterol.
Statins inhibit cholesterol
synthesis through
the HMG-CoA reductase
inhibitor mechanism.
Bempedulic acid
does it from the
beginning with the
citric acid cycle.
The PCSK9 inhibitors decrease
receptor degradation.
Okay, so they're going
to stay there at the
membrane and stop the
receptors from being degraded.
And then inclaristrin
will bind to mRNA and
it's not going to produce
PCSK9 to begin with.
Drugs to reduce
triglycerides, we're
going to have nicotinic
acid that they're
going to stabilize,
free fatty acids.
Fibrates will activate
lipases to degrade VLDL.
And then niacin is the only
one that can raise HDL levels.
So in summary, I will
say, please be really
familiar with the
mechanisms, the
adverse effects, and
the drug interactions.
The statins, you should
understand, they're well
prescribed in the country.
So at some point in
your careers, you're going
to be exposed to them.
So I would say have a
good basis of statins
and how to initiate
and what to do about
liver function tests
and drug interactions
and when to draw a
creatine kinase level.
So from a previous lecture,
I want to give this
question. We have a 63-year
-old male presenting to the
ED with precordial chest
pain. He states that this pain
is often precipitated by
stress or exertion and is
quickly relieved quickly
by rest or nitroglycerin.
There is evidence of ischemia
during stress testing.
Angiograph demonstrates
narrowing of several major
heart vessels. Which of
the following would be
most likely to worsen
the patient's condition?
So we know he has angina.
Probably this is stable angina.
or angina of effort, and
he's given a nitrate.
And remember, we know
that this is not Prince
metal because we see
that there's beta
blockers here as choices.
If it was Prince metal,
remember, you'd get
the unopposed alpha,
kind of like what happens
with cocaine overdose.
And you actually would have
worsening with beta blockers.
So with Prince metal or
vasospasm, we would give a
nitrate or a calcium
channel blocker. Okay, so we
know that's not the case.
This is angina of effort.
So what's going to worsen
the patient's angina?
Is it acebutylol, atenolol,
metoprolol, natolol,
or propanolol? So looking
here, I would probably say
the best answer or what
would be the best for him
would probably be either
B or C because what we
know about those two, the
reason why they're well
used in cardiology is because
these are both beta 1,
okay?
Natalol and propanolol have
both beta 1 and beta 2.
And I would say that we
don't have anything saying
that he's a asthmatic or
he's a smoker or he has COPD.
So I would say that they could
probably be used as well,
Okay, if this was somebody
that had, you know,
asthma, I would probably
say no to those two as well.
Remember, with beta-2
block in the lungs, you're
going to get bronchospasm,
that worsens angina.
Beta-2 in the vessels
might cause some basal
constriction, especially
if we're talking about
those with peripheral
vascular disease, and we
don't know anything about
that. And then beta-2
block in the liver
would stop conversion of
glycogen to glucose, and
that can cause hypoglycemia.
We know nothing about
him being diabetic.
So what's special
about acebutylol? I
thought it was a beta
-1 selective, and it is.
But what's special
about acebutylol?
Well, hopefully, you're
talking about ISA,
Intrinsic Sympathomimetic
Action. And why is that?
Well, because if you have
this action, that means this
medication can behave like
a partial agonist. And
if it behaves like a partial
agonist, you can actually
increase norepineprin, and
that would increase the
workload of the heart or
affect the demand of oxygen.
So this one, even though
it's beta-1 selective,
it would not be the
best choice because
of the intrinsic
sympathomimetic action.
Okay? So, again,
hopefully this clears up a
concept for you that
I think is important.
So, if there are any other
questions, please let me know.
Until then, have a great
day and I'll see you soon.
Thank you.